A Guide to the John W. Daniel Papers, 1893-1910
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John W. Daniel Papers, 1893-1910
The Library of Virginia
21683
36 leaves and 12 pages
John W. Daniel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Glenna Whybrew, Lynchburg, Virginia, 19 February 1940.
Biographical Information
John Warwick Daniel was born 5 September 1842 in Lynchburg, Virginia, to William Daniel, Jr. (1806-1873) and Sarah Ann Warwick Daniel (d. 1845). Daniel attended Lynchburg College and Locust Grove Academy, but left school when the Civil War began. Commissioned a lieutenant, he rose to the rank of major and received a crippling wound at the Battle of the Wilderness. After the Civil War, Daniel began practicing law and entered politics. He served in the House of Delegates from 1869 to 1871 and in the state Senate from 1875 to 1881. Daniel was elected United States Senator by the Virginia General Assembly in 1885 and served from 1887 until his death. He represented Lynchburg in the 1901-1902 state constitutional convention, and was considered a potential vice-presidential nominee at the 1904 Democratic National Convention. Daniel married Julia Elizabeth Murrell (1850-1937) 24 November 1869. He died 29 June 1910.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1893-1910, of John Warwick Daniel (1842-1910) of Lynchburg, Virginia, and United States Senator, consisting of correspondence concerning rural free mail delivery in Virginia counties; the Civil War, including the 14th Virginia cavalry, Confederate records, the steamer St. Nicholas, a Daniel-edited column in the Richmond TIMES-DISPATCH, and complimentary books on Robert E. Lee and Stonewall Jackson sent to Daniel; free coinage; Daniel's speeches; requests for an appointment as a Washington D.C. Capitol policeman and for a commission in the United States army; the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities and the 1907 Jamestown Exposition; an invitation to speak at Easton College in Manassas, Virginia; Daniel's reelection to the Senate in 1910; and a promissory note. Papers also include predictions on the 1894 congressional elections in New York and Virginia and which party would control the United States Congress.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
John W. Daniel Papers, 1898-1904 (LVA accession 21589).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1888-1910 (LVA accession 21623).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1887-1910 (LVA accession 21636).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1874-1914 (LVA accession 23923).
John W. Daniel Letter, 18 July 1904 (LVA accession 27993).
Contents List
- Letter, 18 October 1893, from John Morton (ca. 1847-1902) of Richmond, Virginia, to Daniel regarding payment of a promissory note, and includes the promissory note, dated 12 July 1893, from Daniel to James Doddridge Patton (1850-1925) of Richmond.
- Predictions, 30 October 1894, made by Daniel and Clarence E. Young on Virginia and New York state elections, as well as which party will control Congress after the elections.
- Letter, 23 May 1895, from Charles P. Latham (b. 1844) of Richmond to Daniel discussing "free coinage."
- Letter, 15 December 1900, from William Wallace Scott (1845-1929) of Richmond to Daniel congratulating him on a recently delivered speech.
- Letter, 30 August 1904, from the B. F. Johnson Publishing Company to Daniel informing him he will receive books on Lee and Jackson with compliments of the author, Mary Lynn Williamson (1850-1923).
- Letter, 27 March 1905, from John Lyon Hill (1838-1909) of Augusta County, Virginia, to Edwin Edmunds Bouldin (1828-1912) of Danville, Virginia, discussing the actions of the 14th Virginia Cavalry regiment during the Appomattox campaign, 8 and 9 April 1865.
- Letter, 11 April 1905, from Daniel to the Clerk of the Halifax Circuit Court inquiring about Confederate records.
- Letter, 19 March 1906, from Daniel to Fred Myers of Seattle, Washington, extending personal greetings.
- Letter, 24 August 1906, from William Stapleton Gooch (1858-1933) of Richmond to Daniel requesting an appointment for Robert P. Talley of Richmond as a Capitol policeman in Washington D.C.
- Letter, 8 January 1907, from Thomas W. Buckey to Daniel congratulating him on a recent speech.
- Letter, 16 January 1907, from Robert Alexander Lancaster, Jr. (1863-1940) of Richmond to Daniel regarding the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities and the Jamestown Exposition of 1907.
- Letter, 12 March 1907, from J. W. Pierson of Loudoun County, Virginia, to Daniel requesting Daniel sign a petition for a rural free delivery route.
- Letter, dated 19 March 1907, from Henry H. Taylor (1853-1908) of Loudoun County to Daniel requesting he sign Taylor's application for a rural delivery route in Loudoun County.
- Letter, 21 March 1907, from Thomas Benton James (1841-1915) of Loudoun County to Daniel asking that he not sign a petition for rural free delivery.
- Letter, 25 March 1907, from Pierson to Daniel asking if Daniel had signed the petition.
- Letter, 4 April 1907, from John Abram Hooker (1867-1958) of Prince William County, Virginia, to Daniel requesting Daniel's endorsement of two petitions for a rural free delivery route in Prince William County.
- Letter, 16 April 1907, from Taylor to Daniel asking about the petition Taylor had sent.
- Letter, 7 June 1907, from James Nalle Boyd (1850-1915) of Richmond to Daniel concerning some business plans.
- Letter, 17 January 1908, from William Alexander Anderson (1842-1930) of Richmond to Daniel recommending Arthur Campbell for a commission in the United States Army.
- Letter, 25 January 1910, from Thomas Harlan Lion (1867-1938) of Manassas, Virginia, to Daniel extending an invitation to speak at Easton College in Manassas.
- Letter, 28 January 1910, from B. F. Johnson of Richmond to Daniel congratulating him on his reelection to the United States Senate.
- Letter, no date, from Frank S. Woodson (1851-1922) of Richmond to Daniel commenting on Daniel's editing the Confederate column in the Richmond Times-Dispatch, includes a clipping from the Salem Times-Sentinal.
- Letter, no date, from Frank Huger (1837-1897) to Walter Herron Taylor (1838-1916) of Norfolk, Virginia, requesting information on the Civil War activities of the steamer "Saint Nicholas."
- Petition, no date, signed by 87 inhabitants of Amherst County, Virginia, requesting rural free delivery service.